I think we got it.
Okay.
Before Asli will start, I will just take five minutes to take you
through this workflow that we have been using until now in
Slicer for Fusion 360. And then Asli will take you through
the workflow of 2D to 3D generation, and then fabrication.
So we will jump directly in
the tutorial,
and I will share my screen.
And
so Slicer for Fusion 360 is a very easy and intuitive
program. That's why also we have been using it faithfully,
I can say.
It is a very easy interface. I just want to tell you, it accepts 3D
files like STL and OBJ. Of course, they need to be watertight.
And it has four steps. So
here you can see my model opens and the head is lying down.
So I will open it again, and I will choose Z as an
axis to open it correctly in the correct axis. Yes.
And it has four steps. The first step is to define
your laser cutter. So you define your laser cutter
by creating a new manufacturing setting in millimeter or inches.
You put the size, the thickness, and those ones, you can leave them zero.
This is the margin.
And then once you have set up your laser cutting area,
you can save it. You can select it.
So you can see down here that it has updated. These are my boards.
This is the thickness of my material.
And then you can choose between stack slices,
you can choose interlock slices,
you can choose
radial slices,
and
folded panels.
So now in each of the strategies, you
can customize them. If you choose stack slices, for example, you
can see here the manufacturing settings, so you can directly go to laser cut.
So if you choose stack slices, you can
change the slice direction,
and it will automatically update.
You can modify the form and make it hollow.
Sorry. And you can see
how much,
and apply. So it will update
the boards.
Hmm.
It didn't like so hollow, I think, because I went with the nose.
Okay.
Okay, there is something wrong.
Oh. And also, I don't know why it doesn't do it hollow, but also it will show you.
It did it, but it doesn't visualize it. It has some bugs.
It will show you the assembly steps, so you can go one
by one and
assemble it.
So
here. It will visualize it in cardboard.
You can change, if you want, the type of slices, and if there are errors,
it will give you red. And for this one, for example, you can as well
change the slice direction.
But you can also add
more by clicking add more slices. You can move your
slices wherever you want.
And you can reset and equalize again, or you can delete some if you want.
That one will export. You can get the plans here.
Now it's red, but many times it is red, but it makes sense.
You need to see the assembly process to understand if it will work or not.
Sometimes it makes it red because it's hollow.
And you can choose here DXF in millimeters, and you're ready to laser cut.
So this is very nice and very easy process
using the Slicer for Fusion 360 to translate from a 3D STL
or OBJ, three-dimensional model, watertight, to fabricatable files
directly for the laser cutter. And that was from my part,
the first part of the tutorial.
Now Asli can start.
Hello, everybody. This is Asli.
Thank you, Anastasia, for the introduction to Slicer for Fusion.
I think it will be a good
start, and also we'll come back to it at the end of the workshop.
So as Anastasia introduced me, I am from VAAG
in Amsterdam,
from Textile Lab Amsterdam node. And at VAAG, we are
executing a project called Renaissance, which is an Erasmus Plus project.
If you're in Europe, you know Erasmus Plus projects.
That it is a Europe-wide
project for education,
where we look into developing AI-driven curriculums for manufacturing, art, design,
and architecture
educations. And this is just the first year of the project, and we're looking
into ways where we can implement
AI-supported workflows in our processes as designers, artists,
architects. And I am myself an architect, and I have a background in
computational design, digital design, and fabrication for many years.
And I also teach at universities
in the first years mostly, but also in fabrication studios.
So this is a brief introduction to the course. Let's start. Jump in directly.
First,
I did the
presentation in the Miro board so that afterwards I can share the link with you,
and then you can go through it easily yourself, and the links will be easier for
you to follow. And then we will do the tutorials together.
And let me start with this. So we will look
into, as
Anastasia said, we are in the second week of Fab Academy, so this
workflow was designed thinking about the second week of Fab Academy, but it can be
applied to
other situations and contexts, obviously.
But since we are doing the digital bodies, so we are looking into bodies and how we
can create 2D images out of them, how we can create 3D models out of them, and then
turn them into fabrication files for laser cutting.
So it follows an ideation to design to fabrication workflow, and in the
ideation, we will look into preparing 2D visuals, and we will use multimodal image
generation. So you'll use image to image generation in
Using AI. And we will use text prompts as well to further explain what we want.
And then we will move on to preparing 3D models.
There we will have image to 3D generation using AI again,
but we are humans, and human in the loop is really important.
Before we can move on to fabrication where we deal with real world consequences, we
need to check our models, and we need to make sure that it is actually what we want
to make because digital makes everything possible in the
digital world, but they are not possible sometimes in the real world.
And then we will move on to preparation for fabrication.
And there is, Anastasiia said one option is the slicer, but the other one is
I will introduce a workflow that I followed where I looked into making my own tool,
like a slicer,
and I will show you how to use that one and the process of getting to that
using AI.
So let's get back to the beginning.
So first, before we start, I hope everyone had a chance to fill in
the pre-training survey. It is important for my project, Renaissance project.
If you were able to fill in, I'm really grateful.
And I would like to give a shout-out to Laura Muth's project from last year from
the computational couture week. And she did a very nice project, so
when I share the link with you, you can have a look at how she combined
image and
text to image workflows and also image to 3D
workflows using AI for design.
So let's start.
As Anastasiia said, we will use today Gemini and Tripo.
So if you were not able to
download it or, sorry, create a...
Sorry, I'm trying to find my chat here. Yeah.
Create a linkit. You can do it here for Gemini. I shared it in the chat.
And also for Tripo, you can go to studio.tripo.ai
and create an account there. We will use the free versions, and
so please don't start using them yet.
But if you want to go more open source and
models that you can run locally, obviously, given the fact that if you had a
powerful computer and graphics card, you can go to Hugging Face,
which
is like a platform where you can find different
models for making text generation, language translation, image generation, video
generation, 3D modeling. So for image generation, you can use
instead of Gemini or ChatGPT, you can use Flux.2, for
example, or for 3D modeling, you can use...
Where is it? Tradus.2, sorry, or Hunyuan
3D.
You can use them. They have very limited credits online, so you cannot use them
fully when you use them online. But if you download them and use them locally, then
you can use them however you like.
So let's move in, in
Gemini.
So we have a
sort of interface like this where we can import images and as well as we can
write text there. So what is important here is that I always,
in my example, started with a very basic
make human model and gave some prompts to it and
see what kind of outputs I can get out of it.
So I will walk you through the general prompt structure that I use.
Here, the prompting unfortunately becomes a little bit important.
So here you can use, for example,
with your image, transform this human figure into material.
So
wooden
blocks, keep the pose same, unchanged, the camera angle
unchanged, or you can say also change the pose to this and that, emphasize surface
quality. So you can say that it will be textured or it could have joints or
smooth or transparent, et cetera. And you can also say if you want more background.
So let's go through some examples.
So
you can also draw on top of your drawings in Gemini.
So when I bring in
an image like this and I say... Sorry,
just use this.
You can also click on your model and then sketch on it.
So this is what I used.
I'm going to save it for now
and get back to this, and then you hit obviously submit, and then it
will start creating. The reason that I use Gemini for this is that you have more
free credits, daily credits with Gemini for image generation.
But also, ChatGPT does not like nude people, although
they are
3D digital. And
so it cannot go beyond its guardrails, and
even though you try to convince it, it doesn't allow you to create alterations,
modifications on nude bodies.
So as you see,
it generated
an image to the image that I can then download and use.
But as I said, you can also look into different kind of material
qualities or
defragmentations of the body and also include more important
information about its construction, like joints and dowels and whatnot, or
create different kind of structures and more natural structures around it and
extend it a little bit beyond the body itself.
Or like this example, you can also voxelate it
and to be able to voxelate it in the scale that I want, I
gave the human height and then gave the number of
voxelation,
the size of the voxelation cubes. Voxelation is like pixels but in
three-dimensional. So pixels work in two dimensions, and
voxels work in three dimensions. But before giving this, for example,
it gave me a Python code where I could do this on my computer.
But then I had to say that I want the appearance of voxelation, so I
do not want to actually compute the voxelation and understand how many voxels there
will be. So then it was able to give me this output.
You can also modify the body with the pose itself
and copy and paste parts of the body Again, it needs a little bit
further definition of
what you want to do. And for example, if you do not say, "Make them morph with the
body," then it just copies it and leaves it there, and sometimes it's in front of
it, or sometimes it's next to it, but it never morphs with the body.
Or you can do other kinds of
modifications or give different prompts,
where you can create different textures on the body and also different finishes.
So here, from this point onwards, I wanted to not only
do the first
image generation but also do some further modifications on it.
So you can also say, "Increase negative bump in golden colors," which means is that
bump is a little bit of a technical term for rendering on computers.
It is for the textures that they apply on the 3D models.
It creates sort of an extension and
extrusion on parts. But if you have the bump negative, which means that it goes
inwards. So here, when I create the negative bump, it goes
down, or it gives the appearance of going down.
So because this is a 2D image, it will not be able to do that.
So you see, when you say increase negative bump from this smoother version, it
moves on to a little bit deep
cracks.
You can also change the pose, as I said.
"Give the human rodents the thinker pose."
And then you can say, "Remove the background and the blocks under the human.
Just keep the human." So you have the human.
And then you can also incorporate transformations, ask to make some
transformations. So I said, "Scale the left foot by half."
And then you see the foot is slightly scaled, but it's not
exactly half of the original size.
So what it means is that you can ask for transformation commands because it does
semantic evaluation of what you said. It cannot do precise transformations.
So if you want to do precise transformations, like cuts, trims, selections, and
exact boundaries, you need to go back to your
good old tools of Photoshop or GIMP or any other image alteration, image
modification software you use, and then use it and then bring it to AI for more
interpretive transformations. So this is another example of where it fails.
So I said I put these points on it, and then
I asked to create holes using these as center points, but
I asked the holes to
be same and uniform, but it was not able to create them in
the same size. And you also see that it gave me a little bit more than what I
asked for. I think it decided that the belly button also needed to be
hollowed out.
Or slicing the model from where it is indicated with red and
deleting the arms, legs, and head, keep the texture of the body, make the
background white. So you see that that is also very interpretive, and it's not
exact.
So going back, you can
also think about adding some
texture yourself by
overlapping,
juxtaposing a texture image and the human,
as you see, and then ask to
scale the texture, but it does not show it, but the bump is
scaled here,
as you see.
Again,
the background is removed. The optical illusion is applied as a bump layer.
These textures and bump layers are quite important because then they give the
appearance of
non-smooth surfaces. So when you go to 3D model generation,
then they will be more apparent in the
3D model that you create.
Or this was a little bit of a sleep trial to see if I could do this.
And, yeah.
Applying the ruffle as a texture. Again, scaling the texture three times.
Again, it's interpretive. It tries to scale it three times, but it's not exactly
three times bigger. It's just bigger.
So yeah.
This part is for the
2D visuals, and I will just stop now sharing and ask
if you have any questions or if
we should start making our own
models now. Sorry, 2D visuals. For that, yeah.
Do you have any questions?
Yeah. Hi. So first, thanks for introduction.
And
what was the alternative to Gemini? Could you please remind?
It's Flux.
Flux. Mm-hmm.
Flux on Hugging Face.
There are many more alternatives.
If you want a paid version, you can also use ChatGPT.
As I said, it has its own guardrail, so it doesn't allow you to even modify a
simple
Make Human model, but yeah.
For this tutorial, you would like that we work with Human, or we can work also with
other-
You can work with anything. You can work with
what you have started working with, or if you have a photo of yourself, you can
also ask it to
give them appearance of a
digitally designed body without any textures on it.
But I will work on the Make Human again.
Or you think like a photo of a cat.
Could be, yeah.
Okay.
That's a body as well.
And there is a question. Yes, I will share the link to the Miro board with you.
Oh, yes. There were a few more.
I will just share this Make Human model with you,
so that if you want to start with it, you can already download this and use it.
And I will give you maybe five minutes for you to explore the
generation yourself. And if you have questions, we can look into it together
so that we don't go to the next step before we look into explore it ourselves.
So you would like us to go to the Gemini and-
Yes
... try to put a prompt.
Exactly.
And to, yeah, to transform something.
Yeah, to transform. You can generate a few things, one thing, and
I will
maybe share the Miro link now so that you can look at the examples
there, and then
they will help you.
There you go.
Sorry, quick question.
Yep.
By the sound of you. Make sure I wait 10 seconds. Yeah.
Hello, Frederick.
Hello.
Is there any figure that is a bit more easy for beginners than a human? So a human.
Or
I'm a complete beginner. I'm not a designer, but I want to try to learn the
steps of generating the models with the AI.
Well, as I said, I already put the human figure in the chat here, so you can
already download it and upload it on Gemini. And we are using Gemini right now.
So I will share my screen, and we will
insert our figure there, this figure that I shared in the chat with you, and then
we will write some prompts. You can use the prompts from the Miro board easily,
and then we will generate it. So does that answer your question, Alessandro?
Yes. I will try with a human then. So I feel a bit more supported with the prompts
of the Miro board.
Okay.
I will try that.
Thank you.
Yeah, you're welcome. Because that is really difficult the first time to get Gemini
or any other language model to do what you want.
And always the results are a little bit different than what you want,
so that is very understandable.
Can I ask a question?
Sorry, yes.
Did someone say that they have a question?
Yeah. I'd like to ask a question. When you talked about the damping, when you were
describing the image and you told the damping, the bumping, can we generate an
image, can we generate a human model without not having the damping like this?
Because you told that after we generate and we 3D print, we will find a bumping, a
negative bumping. Can we generate on the Gemini and then don't get any
damping, like a perfectly rough surface?
Of course. Yeah. So if you can say that I want a smooth surface, then it will give
you a smooth surface.
Oh, yeah.
Hopefully.
Okay.
It's not always true, but sometimes these things, these bumps that you create on
the texture helps you with generating a more three-dimensional effect, a texture
effect when you go to image to 3D modeling.
Oh.
That's why I wanted to introduce it, but if you don't want to have any kind of
extras on the body, you can also make it very smooth.
Oh, yeah. Thanks.
Yeah. You're welcome.
So the question is, if the models generated on Gemini are type of fully manifold
objects usually. So,
the models that we create on Gemini are not actually models, they are 2D images, so
they are not manifold yet. And the ones that we generate on Tripod, Tripod is
usually really good. So manifold means that if it is watertight or not.
So
if the geometry is manifold, then it means that it's watertight, then it's 3D
printable. So I'm trying to interpret your question text so that other people
can understand. And usually it is quite good.
But we will also go to Blender, and I'll show you two ways where you can
check if an object is manifold or
how Blender can help you make it manifold.
Sorry.
My Gemini said, "Sorry, I cannot generate unsafe images." I wonder if other people
managed. The screenshot that you shared, I-
Sorry?
Couldn't.
Can you ask again, Luisa?
Yeah. I sent the image, the screenshot that you shared, into Gemini,
and I wrote some prompt, and it said, "Sorry, I can't generate unsafe images."
Oh, also.
Did anybody manage?
Oh, interesting.
Let me find a human that does not look nude, because usually-
It worked for me. Sorry.
Hmm?
It worked for me.
Okay.
But they show an image of a
human with the clothes, and I say, "Take off the clothes."
Mm-hmm.
And I want to look like a doll, like, too.
And told why I was using it.
There is a question in the chat. How do you upload the image to Gemini?
Okay. I am going there now, hopefully.
Okay, now we are here. So when you go to Gemini,
you can either click on this and upload files and select your
image from the menu that opens up, or there is another way
where you drag and drop it into Gemini.
And then here you write your own
prompts. And for example,
I can bring another
prompt.
Whoop.
So turn the figure into a soft, inflatable body made from semi-transparent plastic.
I don't want to see the interiors.
So
then we can further say, "Remove the
background
and make the right hand
bigger than the left hand."
So you need further modifications because now it shows the hand.
You can go back here and then click on Edit Prompt, make the right hand bigger than
the left hand,
remove the
original
right hand. Let's see if this works.
Whoa.
Yes, Siva?
Yes. Hi. It also told me that it can't generate unsafe images,
so I'm just trying to search for
another image to try.
Okay. I will also search for...
I have a question, sorry.
Yeah.
I'm here trying to upload the screenshot of the model to Gemini.
But I don't know why I can't do it because it says that it only allows me to
download it if I have the pro version of Gemini.
So I don't know how to do it again.
So you need to download the
pro version?
Okay. I don't know. I'm on the Gemini.
Mm-hmm.
Okay.
Every time I try to upload a picture...
Can you show me again so I know if I'm doing the right thing?
Please. Thank you.
Yeah, no problem.
So maybe
we go to
the Gemini.
Mm-hmm.
Are you here in gemini.google.com/app?
Are you there?
I was on Gemini. I don't know if there's a different version of Gemini.
Okay.
So if you go to gemini.google.com/app-
Mm-hmm
... then
here, click on the plus sign and upload files, and then select your
file that you want to work on, and then upload it here.
And then you can either add a few things that you want to do here, or
you can write your prompt here to modify it.
Or you can also start with nothing.
And let's see if I
make a
standing
human
figure
with a soft inflatable body.
The interesting part in this is that when you write
a text,
what the model will do behind, what the LLM will do,
is that it will create an image.
Mm-hmm.
So if you already start with giving to the model an image,
you're already one step ahead.
Mm-hmm.
So that is why, for example, I
don't have much control over the proportions of this human, but if I give an
image input, then I have a little bit more control over the proportions,
the pose, a little bit about the texture as well.
Yeah.
And I'm going to paste on the chat the two slides that we've seen
in the digital bodies
PPT, the presentation, the class-
Mm-hmm
... of how the model actually works.
I am seeing very interesting examples from the chat here.
I haven't had a chance to look at them. They're quite interesting.
Wow.
Should we say that we are all good to move to the next step?
Yeah. Are there any other questions?
No. Then we can definitely move to the next
step, which is... Wait, I will just look at that.
Sorry.
Which is to-
There's a question.
There's a question?
Yeah. Sora?
Sora?
Somebody raised their hand, yeah.
Hey.
Okay, no question.
Okay. But you can stop me anytime. I prefer it like that.
Otherwise, it feels like I'm talking to the void when I'm looking at the screen.
So if you feel like you want an answer now, just stop me.
And yeah. So the next part is looking into Tripod 3D.
You have the link here. Did I share this link? I will share the link again. Whoop.
Sorry.
So please, please, please, do not use it now because if you use it now with this,
it will use a lot of credits.
Okay.
So here we will use Tripod. Tripod turns image to
3D models. You can download them. Usually,
game designers use these,
but people like us also use it. And Tripod is the sort of the best that gives you,
as was it Tex who asked it?
The best solutions for
3D printing or fabrication. For example, Trellis, also this free
Hugging Face model that I suggested at the beginning,
also can create 3D models, but it does not
immediately let you download an SCR file.
It lets you download a GLB file, which is mostly used for
game design, not fabrication. So this is for you
to
make sure that you remember what we need to do, but I will go through them now on
Tripod Studio. So here, we click on 3D workspace, and then we
have a screen like this.
There you can use
an image
to begin with. So any photo that you have, you can also use it, but you can
use one of the photos or the models that you have made to
start exploring it. And you upload the photo here in
this corner.
We can select it together.
And since
yours
will have the default settings, it will be slightly different than mine.
So make sure that you turn the texture off, because when you turn the texture on,
as you see, we use a lot of credits. But for
fabrication, we don't need a texture.
Texture is the image that is
applied to the body or a 3D model after
the topology geometry is created, such as in the
small boy model that I showed you. But we don't need the texture for fabrication,
so we can turn it off and save on credits.
And in terms of topology, triangle topology is the most suitable for,
again, fabrication. So use triangulation rather than quad mesh.
And for the poly count, as you know, or as you might know, it is quite
important. Obviously, the bigger the poly count is, usually the greater
the resolution is. But it also means that
the file sizes get really big, and
also it makes
The computer lag a little bit when you want to go to fabrication afterwards,
because it means that there are a lot of points on the model that it needs to
account for to make the
watertight shape.
But low poly means that then you have a little bit less resolution, but maybe at
this scale, we are not 3D printing.
We are not using this for
game design.
We are not going to use it as a digital asset, which means that we are going to
fabricate it with laser cutting, so we can go for
low poly count and decrease our file size.
I will just show you a few things. So for example, this has a little bit close
to 500,000 vertices,
which is quite nice.
But maybe
this has around 220,000 vertices,
which is obviously a little bit less defined than the previous
one. But also, it does not matter if we're making this
out of cardboard or fabricating it with laser-cut pieces.
So I would suggest you to go for
maybe 200,000, 300,000, and if you feel like you cannot
capture
all the details, then you can increase it.
But obviously, when you generate one model, then you lose 15
tokens. So anyway, and I think you start with 200.
And, okay, how Tripod works is that it gets an
image,
and it's diffusion modeling, so it sends in light and then imagines what the back
of the model would look like. So it doesn't know it, but it imagines it.
If you go for, obviously, paid versions, then you can add more views into it,
left, right, and back. But with the non-paid version, you don't have that
option. But as you see, it does not do a really bad job
while imagining what's happening at the back.
Or here, if you look at this,
only having this view, it was able to interpret
what it would look like, and it's not that bad.
And here, when we come down, again, it comes with the best
quality AI model, but to be able to download an STL file, you
need to go with in the legacy
AI model.
Then you hit Generate, and then your file or your 3D model will start
its generation. And then when it's done,
it will appear here,
and then you can rotate around it
and check it. For example, this is not a good one.
Maybe with 50 vertices, it did not do a good job.
But around 200,000,
it's not really that bad. And then once you're done, you hit
Export, you select STL from this list, and
then export the model. This will download your
STL file to your computer.
So now
we can start trying it out ourselves.
So if you go to studio.tripod.3d.ai, you can
start your own 3D generations from your images.
And if you need
an image to begin with, I will again share this image that I was using here.
And to be able to remember what
settings I used, you can go to the Miro board and look at the settings there.
And meanwhile, I can answer some questions if you have any questions.
Could you do it again in Tripod with one of the images of the chat?
Okay, let's see.
And share the screen.
Okay.
Now,
I have downloaded
this
model,
this one,
from the chat.
And as I said, we go to general settings first, make sure that the texture is off.
We have the triangle topology, which means that it creates triangular faces between
three vertices, not pod mesh, which is four
vertices form a face. And then I have, let's go with
300,000 poly count, and then
go down, make sure that our
AI model is legacy. And then
let's see.
Are there any questions while it is generating my content here?
Actually, yes. Ah, sorry.
Sorry. Is there a reason you're using the legacy model as
opposed to the best quality or the fastest and balanced, number three?
Yes, because
I have the free version. If I use the best quality version, it doesn't allow me to
download an STL model-
Okay
... with the free version.
Thank you.
So this is what I have. Maybe increasing
the poly count would have given me better definition.
So maybe let's try that one as well.
When you export it, where do you export it to?
There's different ways you can export it, I can see.
So this here, you select the STL, and then
Sorry. This was a quad model, so it doesn't allow me to download that one.
So you export it,
and then it just downloads the STL.
Do you see a different behavior, Tina? Was it you who asked the question?
Sorry. Yeah, no, it's fine. It works.
It was just the-
It works
... next part that was sent to Blender, et cetera. So just wondering.
But yeah, I see.
Yeah.
Thanks.
You're welcome.
So yeah. Now this has
more definition
to it than the previous one.
But I must say that the scales on
the
fish part is a little bit lost, that scale effect.
Are there any other questions?
Yes, I have a question. When I have uploaded my
model to the workspace, it is now dimmed out.
The whole left panel
is now sort of dimmed out. I can see the model that I've uploaded onto the
workspace, but I can't access anything, any settings or anything further.
On the left?
Yes. You know when you upload your image-
Mm-hmm
... it's gone into a panel on the left-hand side of the screen.
Yep.
So now that entire panel has become dimmed or grayed out,
so I can't use it. Have I done something wrong?
I brought in a JPEG, maybe it had to be a PNG?
No, it supports JPEG as well, so it should not be the problem.
Okay.
But shall I walk you through it? Maybe you-
Sure.
Yeah, so here, you can also, instead of dropping it here, you can
select this box or click on this box
and then
select an image.
Let me select a JPEG.
Other quite... Okay.
As you see, it's a JPEG.
Yeah.
And it uploads without a problem.
Maybe it's the image I selected. I'll try a different image.
Okay.
Also, sorry, I need some help, I think.
Yeah.
Is that okay if I share my screen, because I cannot export my model?
Yes. Mm-hmm.
So I
created a HD model.
Mm-hmm.
I removed the texture, so to reduce, and the poly count is
okay right here.
Mm-hmm.
Or should I make it less?
No, but I see that you have a quad topology, not a mesh
triangular topology.
Sorry, what should I do?
Now you have the triangle selected, but in this model, you did not have the...
Can I show you my screen,
Luiza?
Mm-hmm.
Okay.
So this, as you see, says quad here. It is a quad topology.
Oh, not triangle. Okay. Not really the same, but I will try to find it. Uh-huh.
Okay, so with quad, it's possible to export, right?
It's not possible to export STL. As you see, it doesn't allow me to export
STL with quad.
Mm-hmm.
So what you need to do is you need to regenerate your model, but using the triangle
topology rather than the quad topology.
Okay.
Do that, and after you select quad or triangle, you need to
hit Generate again.
And is there a way to export it?
After you generate the model-
Mm-hmm
... with triangle topology, then it will allow you to export it as an
STL.
Mm-hmm.
Share your screen again so that I can follow along.
Yes. Mine actually was a triangle, and it was already in a
triangle in Cura,
and
H 2.5, as you said. And I removed the texture.
And poly count is very low now. Is it okay?
Or, I mean-
Let's see. I don't think that that would have an effect on the-
Okay.
Maybe I can stop share. I mean, it's just because I don't want to take a lot of
time. I mean, at the beginning, it was already triangular, so
I don't know why it didn't allow. So maybe I can stop now, you can continue, and
then it's
generated. I can share again.
Okay. Because you want to-
Oh. Now try to export it. It's here now.
Mm-hmm. Wait, I don't like things.
Export is the purple button here.
Oh, sorry.
Here.
Now I see. Mm-hmm.
Oh, it's good. So probably it was because it had
grids. Yeah, that's why. Okay.
It was a quad model probably. Can you go back to the previous one?
The one that you showed me that was a-
It's probably this one.
This. Mm-hmm.
Yes. Look here. Do you
see? It says the topology was quad.
Oh, okay.
Okay?
Okay. Thank you so much.
No problem.
Okay, any more questions?
So now we can 3D print it directly?
I mean, yes, maybe. You need to take it to your slicer software.
Fusion... Sorry. PrusaSlicers are quite good at mending the
gaps, so it should not be a problem, but for our
own sake, I don't know.
It's also that if it is very heavy, you can make it very light in Blender.
Yes.
Mm.
So for now...
Oh.
Singer, your model came out quite nice.
Okay.
Yeah. So anyway.
Janek, do you want to share your screen so that we can go over it together
maybe?
Okay, I'll try it.
I'm
just working across two screens. Bear with me.
No problem.
Can you see my screen now?
Yes, but I don't see the... Oh, I see the image.
And it's dim light. That's the second image I've tried.
Which image is it? The
running woman?
Yeah, it's the running woman. The previous one was just a Spanish dancer in a red
outfit.
I thought maybe there were too many flounces of material, so I just tried a running
image.
Well, still, I
think a masked image which has a
simple background would work better.
Okay.
I think here it is having a hard time differentiating what is in the
front and what's in the back. That could be the reason.
Okay.
Yeah, so simple backgrounds work better.
Okay. I'll give it another go. Thank you.
Yeah, you're welcome.
I also wanted to... Noel, yeah?
Yep.
Yeah. Hi.
Hi.
I generated the .STL file,
and I opened it in other software called Free CAD, and I could see
the 3D model. So just a question, can I
use this model for a 3D printing?
Yeah.
Okay.
Check the sizes, though, because they are quite tiny.
It uses one unit as height, and one unit in
3D printing software usually uses millimeters as units in this side of the world,
which means that it comes as one millimeter high.
So you need to resize your models.
Okay. I'm new to the 3D model and 3D printing.
So I'm just figuring out.
Yeah.
Thank you.
Yes, no problem. Just sizing will be an issue.
Sure. Yeah.
Yes. I would also like to share that currently
there is a competition on Tripo. I
have put it in the chat. It is called the Tripathon.
And it is open already, and until the
October 5th,
you can submit your projects. And it is
also having some tour open demo days,
and I will put the locations. I think in Barcelona,
it's on the
17th of October
in Barcelona.
So if you are
fascinated now with Tripo, you can
participate in the competition. And I will be jury, so
I can vote for you.
Yes.
So there is this Discord community, and the events, you can find them on the
link.
Online participation.
Sorry, can I ask a question about the competition?
I don't really understand. I saw the link, but I don't really understand what's the
project about. What do we have to submit?
Your creations. Anything.
Anything?
The craziest things. You don't have a brief.
It's the use of the tool for being able to make an
STL 3D mesh model, no?
I think if you look at the
Tripo landing page, the homepage, there's a lot of examples there
to sort of fuel your imagination. But people are doing a lot of different things
with it.
But that's on the landing page?
Yeah, on the webpage.
Okay.
Just scroll down. There's tons of examples that people have done.
I also have a question regarding the generated model.
Yeah.
I tried to download it, but I don't know which
format should I download it with, because the downloaded normal version is
paid, so I don't know how you guys are downloading it.
So
while
generating the model-
Mm-hmm
...
while generating the model, you need to go down here on the left-hand side and
select
H 2.5 Legacy.
Oh, let me see if I find it.
Yeah.
Because by default, it comes with H 3.1, and with the free version,
you're not allowed to download an STL file.
Okay.
So you need to select the legacy model.
I think I lost my generated model. I don't know where it is now.
Well, you're going to regenerate the model again, so it doesn't matter.
Okay.
Because you need to regenerate it from an image again using this model, this AI
model. Not this 3D model. I'm talking about this AI model.
So I...
So upload an image again. Make sure that you have the texture of
triangle topology and any polygons that you want.
Okay.
And then scroll down
and select H 2.5 Legacy
under AI model,
and then hit Generate.
So I click...
Could you share your screen again?
Yeah. Okay. Because I think I lost the other model that I created, or
no. Okay.
Yeah. You know why?
Because the model was generated with a 3.0.
Yeah.
So when you choose the 2.5, it needs to regenerate again.
Mm-hmm.
Can you share it? Yeah.
It's shared.
Are we seeing this? I don't know.
Can you see the-
Yes, we can see.
Okay. So, okay, I think I was going here.
Yeah, upload.
Here?
Yeah.
But are you using-
But before you upload, choose the 2.5
Or as soon as you upload, choose the 2.5.
So I have to upload it first?
Upload the image first.
Okay.
Are you using Tripo?
Uh...
You're using Prism 3.1.
Yeah, it's the other one. Tripo is here, you see?
Mm-hmm.
Here.
No, wait. Sorry.
Oh, Tripo, guys. Sorry. Tripo here. Okay. Upload? Right.
Okay.
I'm just going to try this one.
So
where do I click it now? I just generate it first, or do I have to click somewhere?
Well,
I don't know. I've never used this interface, so-
Go up.
I'll just-
Go a little bit. Scroll up.
It's like P2. Can you click All Models or
what it says there, yeah, Game Ready?
Yeah. No.
Which?
No, it's the correct one.
Yeah.
It's this one?
But it says Native Quad Output, so it's not this one.
No. Go to-
You're using from the studio.tripo.3d.
Okay.
I think you're using Git linked to another LLM model.
Oh, I'm using the wrong link?
It is your account in Tripo?
Hmm.
I don't know, I just clicked the link from the conversation here. I just...
I don't know.
Weird.
No. I don't know. So it's just a different Tripo?
I don't know.
Did you click this link?
Can you send the link again so I-
Yeah
... make sure it's the right one?
Because it seems that you downloaded something that has many different models.
Yeah.
Oh, I don't know.
We would like actually to know what it is.
I don't know.
What is the name?
It's the website.
Oh, I don't know. It's this one.
I don't know.
But okay, I'm going here now. Okay.
Mm-hmm.
So I have to log in first, right?
Yes.
Okay.
Well, we don't see your screen, but we don't need to see it.
We see the previous screen.
Oh, you see the previous screen?
Yeah. We don't need to see your screen while you're making it.
Yes, you can explore STL.
Mm-hmm.
Okay. This gives me a lot of options to do. I click in the 3D impression, right?
No.
3D impression?
Yeah. Let me see if I can
share
what I'm doing.
Are you seeing this? I'm here.
Yeah, you need to-
I'm still here
... click out of this box, somewhere outside of this box.
But it just went here. I don't know.
Okay. Click on
3D printer.
I think it... Yeah, there you go. At this stage, it's asking you what kind of
designing you want to do.
Yeah.
And
functional objects. Yeah, functional objects.
Like this or no?
Select anything. It doesn't matter.
Okay. It doesn't matter.
Yes.
So I'm just going to click Create a Start.
And then Espacio 3D. Select that one on the left upper corner.
Oh.
Next to Tripo. Yeah. No.
Model?
Yeah. Now you're in the same screen as us.
Oh.
Great.
Okay. Now I just generate it, or I click somewhere first?
First, you need to upload your image, and then, yes.
You see, now you have the legacy model.
Okay.
You were able to.
Gemini.
But shall we continue while you're trying this out?
Yeah. Thank you. Sorry. Thank you.
You're welcome. No problem.
I don't mind if I'm still sharing the screen if it's okay.
It's okay.
I just wanted to also say something regarding the images.
I shared in the chat at some point how the model works, how the LLM
generates the file, and you will see that there are two ways.
That the one, basically it creates different views
of the picture, and then it composes them to a 3D model or the
diffusion. There are two different algorithms, basically.
Or the other one is that it makes noise and then it de-noises.
So this means that if you want to make something more precise, it
is better if you have input more pictures.
Like if you put the top, the side, the front, and the back.
But this kind of
calculation, it has this problem that you see many times that you have many
fingers, for example.
This is called the Janus problem.
But it's always better because the LLM works like that, that if you already want to
do a technical design, you provide the different views. That's a parenthesis.
Sorry, Asli.
No problem. But it's also not allowed in the free tier that you cannot input
multi-view. So at this point, it's not
possible for us, but it's good to know that if you want more precision and you
want to
give the input of what's happening at the back and on the sides precisely, and not
let the Tripo or any other 3D model generator imagine it
itself, then you need to give different views so that you are more in control of
what's happening all around the object, 360. That's true.
So let's continue with
Blender a little bit. So
do all of you have a sort of STL file that they can work with?
Great.
Shall we take a break first, bio break first?
I think, and then-
Musical bio break, five minutes.
Before we start again, Maki has a question again about STL file
export.
You need to choose legacy, as Anastasiia put there, before you generate your
model. And if you go to the Miro board, you can see
how you can do it. So you need to do this before you generate the model again.
So you upload your image, and then you choose the Legacy 2.5,
and then generate the model.
Yes. Hello.
Yeah.
I chose Legacy 2.5 and it made it.
Mm-hmm.
And then I tried to export
it.
Mm-hmm.
And I tried to choose send to Blender.
Not send to Blender. You need to-
Oh, okay. Just export?
Yeah, export.
Oh, okay.
Choose STL and export.
And the texture resolution is 4K is fine?
Right. The-
4K.
There is several-
Texture.
Yeah, there is several
selections for texture resolution.
So-
But we are not using texture because-
Okay
... we're going to fabricate it. Well, if you want to use texture, then you use
more tokens, then you have the image-
Okay. So just-
... wrapped around
... push the import.
Yeah, but if you download STL, the texture information will not come with it.
Okay. Yeah, it's okay. So it doesn't matter.
No.
Okay. Thank you. I can try it.
Yeah.
Okay.
So
shall we start again?
Then we will get
back... Now we will go to Blender, because
if you have a model, then we will see how we can
prepare it and further modify it for
fabrication. So here we have the Blender screen.
I will first
import one model.
As I started with saying, the import model is one unit and it's in meters,
so it will have an effect when we send it to the slicer
for laser cutting. But for now, I will leave it as it is.
And
then we have our person in the center here.
We need to have two add-ons to be able to prepare
this
model for
fabrication.
To be able to do that, we need to be able to add them, if we don't have them.
We need to go to Preferences. I'm using a Mac.
I don't know if
places of the menus are different for Mac or Windows,
but I have Mac only. And if you have used them, if you have downloaded the
extensions before, you can go to Add-ons and select them.
But if you haven't had them before, go to Get Extensions under Preferences and
install these two
extensions, add-ons. You can find them by
searching here. One is 3D Print, blah, blah, blah.
If you search it, you can install it.
Since I have it, it doesn't show the install box here, install button here, but
you need to install it by clicking on it or, and also the Bool Tool,
which will allow us to make boolean operations on the object.
And the third one will make sure that we have manifold geometry, which means a
watertight geometry for-
Sorry.
Yep.
We can't see your preferences screen there.
You don't? Oh, thank you for-
No.
Okay. Then I will share my full screen.
Okay. Yeah. Thank you for letting me know.
As I said, it's
really hard when you don't see what others see. I will share my entire screen.
Bear with me for a second. Now we are in the right screen.
So we will go to Preferences. Now do you see my preferences screen?
Yeah.
Okay, cool. You go to Get Extensions,
and then under Get Extensions, you can type the name of the extensions that you
want, and the extensions that we want are 3D Print Toolbox and Bool Tool.
So if you start typing here, Bool Tool,
they will appear under the available extensions, and you need to
install them by clicking the install button next to Bool Tool,
and then they will appear on the installed area
or move to the installed area, and you need to do the same for 3D Print Toolbox.
And after they are installed, you can go to
Add-ons and make sure that they are clicked, which means that they are available as
an add-on inside Blender.
Then,
we have our human here. Since we generated this guy
or this person,
you see that it does not have a flat base, and I might also want to...
But I would like a flat base so that it stays a little bit
vertical and I put it on the table after I fabricate it.
So I would like to create a cut there. How do I do it?
I
add a mesh plane. Before I add it, maybe you can move the
cursor to a location that you want to make a plane,
and
you can also change this location afterwards. But for now, I will put it here.
It's actually where it is. Add Mesh and Plane Mesh.
And after I generate it,
you see that it is a little bit below, so I need to move it a little bit up so that
it cuts through my object. These are the modifier tools here, so you can move,
rotate, scale
any kind of geometry you have. And we move it a little bit up so that
I know that cuts through my object.
And after I'm done with this... Now this is a plane.
So a plane geometry is not solid,
which means that I cannot do boolean operations with it, so that I cannot subtract
or slice my model
with this plane. So I need to make this a solid object, like my plane, like my
model, human model. So here on the right-hand side,
you will
add...
Sorry.
Add Modifier, Generate, and Solidify.
So when I add this,
you will see that
it is
a little bit thicker now.
And then
I will hit
Apply under this. So now I have this object.
Okay.
So this part, I know this could be a little bit too complicated,
intricate, but this part, I also attached a YouTube tutorial
in the Miro board. So if you cannot follow along right now, you can also do it
afterwards, after this workshop.
So we have this guy now and this solidified plane, which is a 3D
box at the moment, and we are going to split this guy
with this plane so that we have a flat base.
We are going to click on the guy and then add another modifier.
Because we added the boolean Bool Tool, now we are able to add a boolean
operator on it, modifier
So we add the Boolean modifier. You see the difference.
We're going to take the difference of it.
So
and then the operant is my object, which is selected, and
then now I'm going to click on the eyedropper tool and select this
plane.
And then you see the plane becomes the object now.
And once I'm done,
I will apply this.
So it appears like nothing has happened
because we still have this plane here.
But if I delete this plane, and you can delete objects in Blender, if you select
the object and hit X on your keyboard, you will have this pop-up open.
Delete selected objects. Delete it, and it's deleted now.
So you see there is a split now between the top and the bottom.
But when I select the object, they are still together.
So to be able to separate them, split them,
after selecting my object, I will go to edit mode.
You'll see something is happening here.
When I
press A on my keyboard,
everything
within the object is selected. And if I hit P,
then it will separate by loose parts,
which means that it will separate the two parts
of the object.
Now you see that they are separated.
And I can leave the object mode. Now I have two different objects.
One is this and the other is this. And I don't need this part, so I can delete it
by pressing X on my keyboard and deleting.
And now my object has a flat base. You can also do these kind of
variations if you want to delete the arms.
As I said, if you want to delete some parts of the model, it's not easy to do it
by asking AI image generation to cut it exactly from
where you want. But you can do it here by, you don't need to follow along with this
one, by adding a mesh and then
moving it up here a little bit,
and let's scale it a little bit,
scale it further,
and move it here.
Oops, sorry. And then rotate it,
and I move it slightly.
So if I wanted it cut exactly here, I would not be able to do it in
AI generation mode, but
I can do it
here in Blender. Or, I could also do it before sending my image to
Gemini or another LLM.
Here again, we need to do the same thing. I will add a modifier.
Oops.
Solidify a little bit of thickness, which is nice, and then I apply it.
I have it now, and then I will add
a Boolean here, difference, select this plane object,
apply. Now again, I have this
separated.
I can go to this,
select this object, open it in edit mode, select all by pressing
A on my keyboard.
I can separate them by pressing P on my keyboard and separate it by loose
parts. You'll see that this is separated now.
And then I can exit the object edit mode, and then
delete this loose part. Yeah. So once I'm done, I have this model.
Now I need to check if I can 3D print it, or if it's a manifold
object or a watertight object. So
you can open this 3D print tab
by clicking here.
Do you see it? Sometimes you don't see it, but if you click on this side, you can
see it. And then I am going to select my object and then
say, "Make manifold." You'll see that it modified a few vertices,
a few edges, and surfaces to make it manifold.
And you need to press manifold
as
you reach zero vertices, zero edges, and zero faces.
Then it means that your model is
closed.
Sorry, manifold and watertight is the same?
Yeah.
Okay. Thank you.
You're welcome.
Sorry, if we don't have this 3D print option on the side,
where can we find
make manifold option?
You cannot find it if you don't have the 3D print here.
Yeah, I don't have, so how to add it?
You need to go to preferences.
Mm-hmm.
Did you add the 3D print extension?
I downloaded Blender, and I edit with Rico
Make Human extension, but apart from that, no.
Okay, so go to get extensions and add 3D print
toolbox.
I would like to make a small clarification.
Watertight is when there are no holes, meaning that if you
submerge the object in a bottle of water, no water goes inside,
meaning that it's closed.
Manifold and non-manifold is not necessarily exactly that.
It also means that there are no faces that they are not attached.
For example, you made something, and suddenly a triangle was going inside your full
object, and it is not attaching at all.
There are no edges that they're open, internal walls, and it's
a little bit different. But just-
Yeah.
If you go into that, there are no self-intersecting parts in your model.
Exactly.
Yeah. I don't want to make it a little bit-
Yeah
... more complicated. That's why for the sake of this, I said that they are the
same, but they are not. So there should be no openings and no self-intersecting
parts to be able to call it a manifold geometry, but watertight is only when it is
a closed object.
Yes.
So,
I don't know who asked the question,
but were you able to find the-
No. Probably I need to first download, and then-
Yeah, you can do it very quickly. It's under preferences, under get
extensions. Do you see my screen now?
I can see. However-
Yeah.
Mm-hmm.
So you type here 3D print toolbox, the name that you see here, and then click
install, and then it will appear.
Yes. I cannot find it. I searched 3D.
Yeah, I cannot find it.
Did you write print? Maybe that will help.
Print. I wrote 3D. Oh, yes, you are right. Okay, perfect.
Thank you so much.
You're welcome.
Yes, Shivam
Yes. Hi.
Hi
I have some non-manifold edges and intersecting faces.
Mm-hmm.
How do we solve that? Or is that the next part?
Sorry?
How do we resolve those issues? I have 19 non-manifold edges and 11 intersecting
faces.
So you click on the Make Manifold on the Cleanup in 3D Print.
So you need to go to this 3D Print tab-
Mm-hmm
... and go to Cleanup.
Yeah. Yeah, I did that.
And then... Mm-hmm.
And then it said,
at the bottom, plus zero vertices, plus zero edges, plus zero faces.
Okay. Then it's fine now.
Okay.
Yeah.
So maybe that is the nature of my 3D model, maybe? Is that the reason?
I don't know, but I also had that. When I Check All, I also had some problems.
It said non-manifold, but I was able to import it to a slicer software afterwards
when I-
Okay
... did the Make Manifold. So hopefully it will resolve the issues.
Okay, awesome. Okay.
Okay. Any more questions?
Shall I continue?
And something else that we can do, if we think that this is too big of a
poly count, we can also go Add Modifier and go to Decimate, which will
decrease our poly count. So you see we have now
94,000
face count, but we can decrease it
if we want to decrease it. So it will obviously
decrease the resolution of our model,
but at the same time, make it lighter for slicing software.
So again, we need to go to this down arrow, click Apply,
and that should be it. And then let's do another manifold again, and then we can go
to, by selecting the object, we can export it as STL.
Sorry. Where did you find Decimate?
Here. Select the object, and then here under the Properties,
Add Modifier, Generate, and Decimate.
Thank you.
You need to have the human figure selected so that the modify-
Yeah.
Can you show it again? Excuse me.
Okay.
Yeah.
So if you do not have the modif- Oh, now I have it, but
select the object, your human figure, and then go to Add Modifier,
Generate, and Decimate.
Oh, we don't see it now.
You don't see it?
Ah, wait, wait. Yeah, wait a second. Yeah.
Okay.
Yeah. Under Decimate, now because I already done this, my face
count is at 67,000.
But if I want, I can, again, change this.
Okay. Now,
we will export this.
Select the object, and then Export,
and then you choose a location, and then write the name of your
model,
Workshop
Human.
Asli, I'm sorry. Can you show the Export button again? Yep.
So where we were under 3D Print- Mm-hmm ...
we had the Cleanup- Oh, okay ... Make Manifold, and then we have the Export.
Mm-hmm. So you need to click this, and then it will open it up. Okay. Thank you.
Mm-hmm. And then you will export it.
And there-
Sorry to interrupt, I'm a bit back.
Yes.
I installed the 3D Print extension, but I don't see that 3D
Print
kind of thing on the side that you have, that one. Okay.
So sometimes it happens that you don't see these here, but there is a small tab
that you can see. If you click this tab, it will open up right away.
Oh, right. Yeah. It's in there.
Good?
Yes.
Yeah.
And sorry, so the setting that I need to have here?
You select your object, and this-
Yes
... this should be closed like this.
When you have it open first, you click on the dropdown menu under, next to Cleanup.
Cleanup, yeah.
And then Make Manifold.
Okay. Just that?
Yeah.
Okay.
And then make sure... You need to do it maybe several times until you see no
vertices,
and
edges and faces are at the bottom, you see how many are modified, until you
see 000.
Sorry, where? Can you show me where I should see 000?
So when you... It just disappears very quickly.
Make, yeah. Manifold.
But when you click Make Manifold, it should appear under the screen here-
Yeah
... with an information.
Oh, okay.
Yeah.
Okay.
And then we do-
Okay, all zero. Okay
... Export.
I see that there has been a lot happening in the
chat.
Oh, yeah.
Mm-hmm. I'm just reading through the chat.
Okay. I think all are answered now.
We can move on. Now we have our model STL downloaded.
Obviously, I need to first select it, and then
Desktop.
Workshop Human,
and Export.
Okay. Now I will go back to
the Miro board again to show you where we are in the process.
As you see, we have done the 2D image generation, image to 3D
generation, 3D model modification and verification for fabrication, and now in the
fabrication preparation process.
Oops.
Sorry.
And now we can either do it with the slicer that
Anastasia showed at the beginning of the workshop, but I was thinking, I started
thinking about this maybe a few months ago, that how, because Slicer
for Fusion is discontinued and it can give bugs now, or it can
shut down, and it's not very reliable now, how can we
make our own version of it? Or how can we use AI to be able to generate our
own fabrication tools with it?
And here I
first asked ChatGPT, "Can you slice a 3D model
STL for laser cutting and give me the XL file?" The DXF file, sorry.
DXF is a
file format that is an interchangeable
Autodesk file format that is used for 2D vectors that
is very reliable, or you can use also SVG, of course, but I find DXF more
reliable. And ChatGPT says, "Yes, I can do that, but you need to
select this and this, or choose this and this and that." And then when I looked at
the possibilities, I said, "We can maybe work with those, but then I think an
interface to be able to choose those would be more ideal, like a Slicer for
Fusion." So I said I want to create a small web app to do that and visualize it
rather than selecting it through here or writing or talking to a model like this
here.
So
I started making a small web app with Lovable.
If you don't know Lovable, Lovable, it allows you to create quick
websites using, again,
language
like English.
You don't need to know coding. You can use semantic languages to generate models,
sorry, websites. And
we started making a rapid first web prototype, but there were a lot of
problems with it. And also it was a good first
quick prototype, but also did not have most of the functions that I wanted it.
And yeah, a lot of bugs in general. And then I wanted to continue working with
Lovable, but then I ran out of free credits very quickly, and I did not want to pay
for it, obviously, and I want to be able to be more in control of it,
and also make it open source. So I said, "Let's move to GitHub." So that we have
this first interface,
the code of the website hosted on GitHub where the code is
stored, and we can track the changes.
And I also made a local
repository or a clone of it so that I can debug and see
transformations easily.
Obviously, I'm not a coder, I'm not an engineer, so I would not be able to do this
without ChatGPT, but I have been fabricating and
designing on computers for so long that I can be able to give the input of what I
want, how I want it, what kind of features this thing needs, or I can
also debug it when necessary. And we needed to do a lot of debugging.
So from this first model
to the final one, so you see that first
I had to look into
uploading different geometries. So it starts with a vase.
It's easier to
slice it. You see the contours here. It slices.
It's one object per slice, and it's not a problem.
It doesn't give you the fabrication order or number of the parts, which is very
important for fabrication, because imagine that you have objects that are really
similar in size. If you don't know the
parts number, you cannot put them together.
So we started looking into that, and I added that, but then
slices with multiple parts did not generate part
numbers on the other side. So we looked into that. So a lot of debugging.
And then the nesting was another problem, again, with multiple parts on one slice.
How do you solve this? And then looking into waffle structures,
that's another possibility that Anastasi also showed in the beginning with the
slicer profusion that you can also do waffle slices.
Initially, it did not generate the slices that I want or the cuts where the parts
can slip together.
So a lot of debugging, testing,
and labeling and alignments and different options.
Then
I was able to come up with a working version now, although the functions that I
want for the future are not there. It is usable now.
And okay, the GitHub version is nice, but it's not accessible for everyone.
So there is a Vercel app, so it allows me to publish it live, and
this is the app
that I sort of created with the help of ChatGPT,
and I will share the link.
But you didn't use agents?
No.
You used the chat?
I used the chat, and because I wanted to be able to be in control of what's
happening all along the
step-by-step because when I tried to, for example, do overnight
executions, but then I did not know what was happening.
So I was not in control of what was happening.
Sometimes I even did not allow it to access my GitHub repository.
I asked where I needed to change in the code, and I went to my local repository and
make the changes myself and then push it to my Git repository to be able to know
exactly what was going on in the app.
So yeah, I was going to write this. Where is my chat?
Here is the...
Yes.
I just saw a question. The core function of this app is you have a 3D
model, but if you want to create it with
a CNC machine, like with chopwood, I don't have the chopwood functionalities, but
milling or laser cutting, you need to slice it in several intervals, usually the
thickness of the material, so that you can
give these slices to the laser cutter and then create the
material objects with them, slices with them, parts with them, and then put them on
top of each other, glue them on top of each other
physically to have
a real object.
So that is the function. Was it clear or do you want me to...
So, for example, for a file for an object like this, it generates the slices,
and you have these slices. When you export them,
it gives you the file that you need to sheet DXF or all sheets
together.
It gives you the files that you need to take to the laser cutter so that you can
use this for laser cutting.
Is that clear?
Yes.
Yes, exactly.
Yeah, wipe coding, I like it, but as I said, it is very important.
You cannot do that, and that is what I wanted to come back to.
As a human, you need to identify the need. You need to specify the features.
You need to evaluate the results and test implementations against real fabrication
requirements and keep correcting technical and usability problems.
So that is really important. If you don't have the expert knowledge, domain
knowledge, experience with it, you cannot wipe code, basically.
So actually the AI does the job, and we do the cleaning.
No. I mean,
a little bit, but you need to specify what AI needs to do.
It does not automatically create waffle slabs, or even if it creates waffle
structures, as I showed you,
the initial
operant is this, and then you need to say that, okay, all the slits need to
come to the middle of each section.
So you need to operate those, and you need to say that they need to be intersected
with the boundary object and trimmed.
So to be able to say these kind of things, you need to have the domain knowledge.
And so, for example, from this to
this afterwards. To be able to get there, you see,
you need to be able to tell what is going on.
And here you see that I have also each piece is called
Written on the slits so that you can also put them back together, assemble them
together, whereas you don't have them here.
And to be able to say what's going on, it's not a magic tool that just generates
things.
FormSlice basically works similar to
Slicer for Fusion, but with less
features now.
But if you come here, let's
open
it from scratch. So you can upload an STL, or you can also drop
an STL file here. So let's put our last
human that we dropped here,
and then-
Asli, do you need to share your screen?
Sorry?
Do you need to share your screen or-
Is my screen not shared at the moment?
No.
It is shared. I see the-
Yeah, I can see
... FormSlice.
Okay. Hmm.
Do you see other people on Zoom? Sometimes I do that.
Luiza, if that is the case-
I'm seeing people.
Okay. If that is the case, go to the upper edge of your Zoom screen and there's
a tab there. One says Meeting.
Okay. Thank you.
I did that a few times, no problem.
Yeah. Okay. So you drop your human, and then you choose the size.
As I said, it comes with
one millimeter, almost one millimeter.
So we need to obviously increase the size.
And
then you can also rotate it however you like,
and then reset it. Well, where did the guy go? Obviously, this is also gone.
Let's make it 200.
And
you can choose here if you want stacked slices, which means that they will be
stacked in one direction, or you can have waffle, which means that it will have a
waffle structure.
Radial slices hopefully will come next. I don't have them yet.
So if you choose stacked slices,
you can choose by thickness or by count.
So if you choose thickness, you can think about material thickness, how much you
want. You can also have space in between the slices.
You can change the offset. Sometimes you need to do this by a little bit
because if there is a point
where the model ends, it cannot calculate with a slice.
I mean, it cannot intersect with a slice, so you might need to move it slightly
down or up. You can also change the order, and then curve
compensation, you can leave it as it is.
Curve is the material eaten away by the laser, because laser
cuts by
burning the material. So by that burning,
a certain amount of the material is eaten away, so it's to counter that.
Curve mode is auto, which means that it's on the outer side and the holes, and then
this is for fabrication. So as I said, you need to be able to label
each part so that you can assemble them afterwards.
And then you can also specify how high, how big you want them to be.
So for double holes,
you need to...
Sometimes when you stack slices on top of each other, with waffles, you don't have
that problem because they come together like this.
But with stacked slices, they can shift a little bit, so you need an inner
structure, and the doubles create these inner structures.
I will not go through them one by one right now.
Experimental nesting is very experimental,
so turn it off for now. You can also have it on.
It takes a little bit longer, and it does polygonal nesting.
If you know different types of nesting, it does not do a very smart nesting.
I need to incorporate a nesting algorithm into it.
And it only does the polygonal nesting for the big
20 or 30 parts for now.
And this is the sheet size. So you select the sheet size here,
and you give a margin so that it does not go to the edge of the model.
And then you choose
part spacing, so what will be the distance between the parts if you're going to
allow
90-degree rotations. If you're using corrugated cardboard, I would suggest you
to not allow it so that corrugations are in the same direction, and then it doesn't
look
awkward. And when you're ready, you can start generating slices,
and then it generates the slices. And you can see it in the sheet layout.
And when you're done,
so it says, "Fit safe layout." As I said, it has a lot of
space in between now.
But yeah. This is for now what it does.
And if you choose the experimental
nesting, it will nest the biggest 30 parts together better, and then it will also
start using these in-between parts.
And when you're ready, you can go to export.
You can export either
all the sheets, only this sheet, or only one slice.
And you can do both DXF and SVG exports here.
And then now,
once you download this,
let's do a sheet download.
This is... Or
it's easier to show this one. So this SVG is ready to be
used at a laser cutter of your choosing.
Any other questions?
A quick one. The green outline that's on the inside, that's just to show where the
adjacent part is-
Exactly
... glued? Yep.
Yeah. Engraving lines. I wanted to add them so that you know where you need to glue
the next part.
Yeah. This is so cool.
Yeah. So what
comes next is
obviously add more features. One is radial slicing and also assembly preview,
debugging and resolving conflicting requirements, which means that when you do one
implementation, it usually creates problems in other implementations, previous
implementations, so you need to
go through, test it with various features together.
So I need to validate it with more users and models to make sure that this is
really reliable. And with every test, I can see more
bugs and correct them. Now, the GitHub project, because I'm still working on it,
it's private, but the idea is to make it public and open source so that other
people can
improve it, inspect it. But also, if they don't want to use a
web app to use it, like Vercel, then they can download it and use it locally.
And maybe to add an LLM-based design assistant on top of this, where you can chat
and you identify, you say, "Create a waffle structure with four-millimeter plywood
and prepare it for
600 to 400 millimeter laser cutting sheet." So maybe to implement
this so the LLM-based designer system can interpret your
conversational language and interpret it as the parameters of the
app.
Oop. Lot of questions.
Yes.
Hi. Yes. So one doubt you already cleared, that preview is a new
upcoming feature that you will be adding.
Mm-hmm.
But some of my slices on the right side panel are
showing me with small amber warning symbols.
Mm-hmm.
And I think those slices are not generated, because in slice preview, it just shows
me like a rectangle.
How do we resolve that? Can I share my screen?
Share it.
Yeah.
Okay.
Can you see this?
Yeah.
So this warning sign-
Mm-hmm
... and this is the slice preview it is showing.
Mm-hmm.
If you click on other slices, it is showing correctly.
Yeah.
But this is-
Okay, this is actually the parts can be printed or laser cut, but it
is because
the label height is too big that you cannot print a label on it or engrave a label
on it.
So-
Oh, okay.
Yeah, sorry.
So if you decrease the... Oop. I will try to show it.
Yeah, if you decrease the label height here,
you might be able to
get rid of this
warning sign. It is also that the piece is too small.
Okay.
Yeah. Then it might also mean that the
previous layer engraving and the, or the next layer engraving cannot be
made.
Oh, okay.
Yeah.
Yeah, sure. Yeah, it is that.
I guess they are still too small pieces.
Yeah.
But this is... Can you go up a little bit? Can we see your...
Yeah, it's a very small object now.
It's 100-
Yeah, so this is-
If you look to the left-
Mm-hmm
... you see that the-
It is small. Yeah
... the size of your object is only the 10 centimeters, and you're trying to cut it
to smaller pieces.
Okay. I understand. Okay.
Yeah. So it's because of that.
Okay. Thank you.
Yeah.
And Silvia?
I am.
So first of all, thank you, Asli. I know very little about digital design, but this
looked impressive, so
kudos from my side. Totally impressed.
So, in my case, I did the
manifold of my object through Blender. It gave me the zero-zero data.
But still, when importing
and trying to slicing it with the same parameter that you had, it tells me that
it's not manifold.
Hmm.
The
STL needs to be further investigated.
Maybe it was not manifold in Blender.
So
I manifold in Blender.
It was not watertight.
Sorry?
Watertight?
Oh, well, I don't know. Watertight?
But yes,
manifolded but not watertight. I don't know.
So anyway, so I manifold it in Blender, but it's telling me through the program
that is not manifolded and cannot slice it.
Mm-hmm.
Hmm.
I'll try with something different.
Yeah.
I know how to solve it in Rhino easier than Blender, to be honest.
I have more-
Oh, yeah
...
more control over Rhino, but so I won't be able to answer that, honestly, in
Blender.
Okay. Thank you.
Yeah.
Any more questions?
I'm sorry. It's not about the tutorial, but you said, in the beginning,
you're going to
put the link for a tutorial, so we can follow through in the end just to make sure
we have everything.
There is a link in the Miro board-
Okay
... she had for the Blender now.
Oh, yeah. Oh, thank you, Anastasia.
I was thinking this Zoom tutorial, but yes, for the Blender
tutorial, there is a link on the Miro board with a YouTube video.
Will the Zoom be available as a video or-
Yeah
... notes? Oh, great.
Yes, but we would like that it is used for personal use to learn and not to
be
transmitted in a classroom of 200 students without credits.
Sure, of course.
Okay?
I'm not really finding the link for the Blender tutorial. Is the...
No, there's none.
Are you on Miro board right now?
Miro? Yeah, I have this up. Yeah.
So here in the Miro board,
this is the zoomed-out part, and if you go in here,
how to cut a model in Blender.
This is a tutorial.
Do you see it now, Rita?
Not really. Sorry.
Do you see my screen now?
Yeah, I'm seeing your screen.
Okay. You need to zoom into the design, in the second phase of the
design, where we do modifications, and this is a YouTube video.
You need to click it.
Oh, I have to zoom in. Yeah.
Okay?
In the design part?
Yes. Under design.
Yeah, under design.
And
3D model modification.
Here.
While you look at it, I will look at the chat.
Asli, would you like us to provide you some feedback about this
tutorial or the experience, or what feedback would you like?
Yes. Thank you. Because we're tying the ends now.
It's the end of the session. So first of all, thank you for joining.
And it was nice because we have our reservations with AI, so it's...
And
so I always like to use it meaningfully and as much as I'm in control
and as much as I don't forget my humanity and my human creativity and understanding
my limitations, understanding AI's
limitations, and working together collaboratively, rather than dumping all my
thought process to it, or
getting all my feedback from it, or asking it to generate miracles for it, because
it cannot do it. So-
So that's what I'd like to do. So I would like you to use AI responsibly first.
Yeah, I agree that
it's really important to demystify AI for creators and what it can do and what it
cannot do, and what we still need to do.
So first of all, if you can go to the Miro board and share
what you have done
with me here. You can also do it afterwards, but it would be cool to see it
here.
The ideation, so what you generated with Gemini, if you can put some photos here
under design. If you can put some photos from, or
screenshots from your
tripod models, and also
fabrication
interface screenshots, that would be nice.
And
there is something interesting that I would like to read, and if you can put your
thoughts and reflections in here, that would be also nice.
And as a last request,
there is the post-training survey that if I may ask you to fill in,
that I will also share the
link with you here on
Zoom. Oh, sorry, not Signal.
But where's my Zoom? Yes, in chat. Then I will be
able to
also provide you with an open badge of completing this tutorial
afterwards. So
if you have done the pre-survey and if you have done the post-survey, I can make
your names and emails and then I can send you the open badge to your emails with
that.
And yeah. But we can
talk about
what you think about this, how you experience AI.
Do you also have AI anxiety like I do?
Because that's my work and that's also what I see everywhere now, so I'm
curious to hear about your thoughts as well.
Well, I can say something.
Yes, please.
I'm concerned about the use of AI, of course.
Mm-hmm.
Using a lot of resources on Earth and
how it's going to change the perspective of everything in a bad way, maybe in a
negative way.
Taking over. We also have to use our brains still, right?
Mm-hmm.
So, yeah. And of course, we hear a lot about all these service centers, et cetera.
The last point, please. Yeah.
We also hear a lot about how much it uses for generating and all
this information input you have to put in it, and yeah.
I think it's a bit scary, I have to say.
I agree.
I think that's a very common reaction, but
I don't have a lot of support for this yet.
But my belief is that technology, when it rolls out, is somewhat neutral,
and it's up to us to decide how it gets deployed and how it gets used.
Unfortunately, capitalism
usually tends to shift things. It tends to dehumanize technologies or de-skill
people. But I'm part of a little collective that is right now
working
on workshops just like this one to help people understand that AI can be used to
great benefit as well. To the extent that it's displacing people like me
from-- I was a software engineer. To the extent that it's displacing people from
some jobs, I think it's opening incredible new opportunities in other jobs.
I'm also sort of an amateur historian of science and technology, and if you look
back, going all the way back to the Steam Age, every time there was a disruptive
technology that came out, there was a lot of concern about how displacing it would
be.
We can't necessarily predict the winners and losers, but it's important to be open
to the change and to be able to roll with it.
And
Asli, I think this is exactly the right way to frame it, is that the human has to
remain in the loop at every stage in the iteration and really
understand sort of what's going on under the hood.
And I think you're exactly right. It's to bring your personal
expertise and knowledge and context to bear on a problem that's important to you to
solve, and using the AI not as the boss, but as the assistant.
And as you can see, sometimes it's not too bright.
But it already knows ahead of time a lot of really interesting
context. And I think if you use it as kind of a mirror to reflect back your own
sensibilities and your own biases,
that in a sense, AI can help us understand better what it means to be human.
Yeah.
My two cents.
Thank you, Kerry. I agree. Only with
one comment that is related to the very beginning of what you said.
It's every technology born neutral.
I think that is not true with AI because it used datas
of people that are usually mostly represented on
internet. So it does not start neutrally.
So it uses
English as its first language, and most data out there
is also in English, and it belongs to certain
cultures and certain people. So this was not born, or when it told
something back at us, it was never neutral from the beginning.
But apart from that, I agree that it needs to be discussed, and it needs to be,
within these kind of contexts, its limits and needs to be
explored, and also needs to be a little bit like, where do we end?
Where does AI start or any other technology start?
We need to explore that further and see in kind of collaborations we can see with
it. And
my husband is a software engineer, and he was also very mortified when he saw what
I was able to do without knowing much.
I know a little bit
programming. So as I said, I'm a computational designer, so I don't start with
blank slate, but I also cannot do this much of coding, obviously.
But hopefully it will not replace the jobs, and we need to move towards looking
into how we can mitigate short-term and long-term impacts of it
in the society as well in terms of job security, too.
But definitely it doesn't hurt to learn about it, because then it empowers us as
well.
I'm very sorry, but I missed most of what you said initially, so I would very much
like to follow up after.
Yeah. Let's do.
Okay. That's fine. Great.
And Shiva?
Hi.
So first of all, this was a great exploration in 3D models and
gen AI to use it.
I'm also quite
reserved when it comes to use of AI.
This might be the most amount of AI used in a month for me.
But
yeah, this was, again, a great demonstration of how to use AI without leaving the
driver's seat, so to speak. So yeah.
Thank you for that
I would also like to add that nowadays,
at least my personal perspective is that
what the humans need to develop more are skills
like policy, sociology, anthropology, so that you can
actually, for example, write the rules for the AI.
These kind of skills are skills that they are going to be more needed.
I agree. Soft skills will be... And how to
find out our human side more, or figure out, explore our human side more.
Yeah, the history of all of those things,
they are very essential for being able to drive the AI where
it should.
Mm-hmm.
Melissa?
Yes. Hi.
I want to tell you something, because
all we see in this class,
come to me once a teacher told us that
AI was going to replace us to the sculptors.
But I think it's a work collaborate between the artist
and the AI, now we can create unique pieces.
And I think
the people in other place, like my
city, because I am from Ayacucho,
we must
lose the scary about these new technologies and think
about the computer and was scary for the
people doesn't know about the use.
But now it's a complement for a lot of works and the artists
like me, it's at all very
important now.
After this class, I have a lot of ideas
for work. And that's all. Thank you.
I'm happy to hear that, Melissa.
I'm really happy to hear that because that was actually our intention, to introduce
you to this
world a little bit, not to feel ourselves lost, but to
see how we can
open up new opportunities if possible.
And if it's not something for us, that's also fair.
Once we know, we can also move on. We don't need to use it.
We don't need to be part of it. But we need to know to be able to decide.
Well, Melissa, nobody will replace the
restoration that you are doing with the stucco plastering, with the plastering of
the rehabilitation of this building. I don't think that it will be replaced by AI.
No. We also do another project as well.
Yes.
Yeah. It's with craft people. They even-
So do things with your hands
...
we work with craft people.
Exactly.
And they say that there's so much that AI can do, and they cannot create lace work,
or they cannot do restoration, or they cannot...
There are these things that are very human. Yeah.
Yes, Julia?
As you were talking about AI and restoration of buildings,
our professor at work, he's working on a project where he does
restoration of buildings with robots, which is programmed with AI.
So, I would not say that this won't change, or
I think there are so many points, so many jobs where we now can't imagine that
AI and robots and new technologies are able to
change those jobs. But I think nothing is
unimaginable at the moment.
I try not to go to those lengths yet.
It kind of scares me to think about that at that moment, to think
the unimaginable.
I don't know. I
try to ground myself on the possibilities.
Yeah, but I agree that
a few weeks ago, I had an anxiety about where we are going, what's going to happen
in 10 years? Are we going to be around still in 10 years? But it's so hard.
But I agree with Anastasia point that we need
clear policy around
how we handle it and how especially big tech handles it.
Yes,
Noel? Or Julia, did you have more points that you want to share or...
Yeah.
Once again, thank you for conducting this tutorial.
I'm basically an electronics engineer who do circuit designing, and I have heard
about 3D modeling many times, many years, but I haven't tried
on this subject. But this gave me more insight
to work on more because, as a electronics engineer, I do prototyping, but
mostly I use
off-the-shelf enclosures for my prototyping. But this gave me more insight.
It gave me
an opportunity to think about to
use a 3D model, customized one,
which is good. And the second thing on AI.
Yeah, AI will advance, but on the restoration point, a few days before I was
restoring one old Sony Hi-Fi system, and AI helped me on looking on old
schematics and to fix that. But again, on the restoration part, our
hands has to go for the restoration.
AI can support us, but AI can't take over. Yeah. Thank you. Thank you once again.
Yeah.
Thank you.
All good?
Yes. Thank you, everyone. Thank you.
Yeah.
Thanks, Natalie.
I would, again, ask you to fill in the form if you feel like it.
It helps me majorly, immensely. You cannot imagine.
But thank you all for joining, and if you want to further the conversation, want to
know more about what we do within the Renaissance project or any other projects
at WAW, I give you my email here, so you can write to me, or I will also
put it on the mural board so you have where to find me.
Yeah.
Basically, the post training is the same, but...
After you have done the training.
After you have done the course, no?
Yeah.
Okay. It's the same.
It's not that lengthy as far as I remember.
Okay.
But it tells you how much you learned and did you learn anything?
Mm-hmm.
Was I helpful to you?
Yeah.
Great. Thank you.
Yeah. Thank you.
Bye.
Bye-bye.